<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A godly and fruitfull sermon preached at Lieth in Scotland by a faithfull minister of Gods holy Gospell</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11923</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22236</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106434</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842150</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842150</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6780</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11923)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6780)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 585:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A godly and fruitfull sermon preached at Lieth in Scotland by a faithfull minister of Gods holy Gospell</title>
                  <author>Murray, John, 1575?-1632, attributed name. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 59, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>W. Jones' secret press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed. 1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Murray on leaf *2r of: Informations, or a protestation, and a treatise from Scotland (STC 14084).</note>
                  <note>Press from STC.</note>
                  <note>The sermon was actually preached in Edinburgh and was printed in London without the authors consent--Folger Shakespeare Library catalog.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6780:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6780:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> GODLY AND FRVITFVLL SERMON <hi>PREACHED AT LIETH IN</hi> Scotland by a faithfull Miniſter of <hi>Gods holy Goſpell.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalme 74</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <bibl>10.</bibl> O God, how long ſhall the adverſary reproch thee? ſhall the enemy blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme thy name forever?</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>22</bibl> Ariſe, O God: maintaine thine owne cauſe: remember thy dayly reproch by the foliſh man.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed. 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6780:2"/>
            <head>To the godly, and Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>IT every where goeth heard with <hi>Chriſts</hi> true Church as I heare, and feare. Neither doe men make that uſe of the miſeries of it, that were fit, but even in affliction eyther fall away, or become faint harted, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. In <hi>Scotland</hi> the <hi>Hierarchy</hi> prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth much, and then <hi>Chriſtes Diſcipline</hi> muſt needs be thruſt to the walles. Yet ſee notwithſtanding how God ſtirreth up ſome to make oppoſition againſt that triple-hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Cerberus.</hi> This Sermon is one playne proofe of it, which was both preached, and written there, and came to my handes by good meanes. I haue cauſed it more plainely to ſpeake Engliſh then the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> phraſe yeelded; And yet God is witnes to my ſoule, that I haue done it, as neere as I could, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any diminution of, or addition to either matter or manner. Such as it is, I preſent it to thee, ayming only at thy benefite, and pleaſure, ſpecially ſpirituall. Farewell, and the Lord giue thee grace to uſe it to all good purpoſes.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:6780:2"/>
            <head>A <hi>GODLY AND FRVITFVL</hi> SERMON, PREACHED AT <hi>Lieth, in Scotland, by a faithfull</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Gods holy Goſpell.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gal: 5.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Stand faſt therefore in the liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made vs free, and be not entangled againe with the yoke of bondage.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>SEeing upon us <hi>the endes of the world are come,</hi> ſaith Paul, 1 Cor. 10.11. and <hi>now the end of all thinges is at hand,</hi> ſaith Peter, 1 <hi>Pet: 4.7.</hi> and <hi>that day of the Lord is comming like a theefe in the night, in the which the heavens ſhall paſſe away with a noyſe, and the elements ſhall melt with heat, and the earth with the works that are ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhalbe burnt up,</hi> 2 Pet: 3.10: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing <hi>Sathan, that great redde dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, knowing that he hath but a ſhort time,</hi> is upon his long chayne, ranging, and raging, drawing downe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s even ſome of the ſtarres, who ſhould giue light in Gods Church, &amp; caſting
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6780:3"/>
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the earth, Revel: 12. and rayſing up falſe Chriſts, and falſe Apoſtles, <hi>ſo that if it were poſsible the very elect ſhould be deceaved, Math. 24.24:</hi> For theſe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes we haue made choiſe of this portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of holy ſcripture, whereby we may be put in minde, and our heartes may be ſtirred vp, to faſten our affections faſt upon that gratious liberty, wherewith the Sonne of God hath made us free from every ſpirituall thraldome, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſtedfaſt through faith, not enta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling our ſelues againe with any yoke of bondage, untill the crowne of that free kingdom be put upon our heads, in the great day of the glorious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of our Saviour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The chiefe butte the Apoſtle Paul ſhoteth at in this epiſtle, is, to eſtabliſh his doctrine concerning true Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the righteouſnes of Ieſus, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through faith, without any mixture of the works of the lawe whatſoever, morall, or Ceremoniall: againſt thoſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6780:3"/>
falſe Apoſtles who had crept in amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the <hi>Galathians,</hi> ſtudying to deceiue, &amp; bewitch them, that they ſhould not be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leeue the truth, to whom the Apoſtle before had <hi>deſcribed Ieſus Chriſt in their ſight, and as it were crucified him amongſt them</hi> by the playne, and powerful prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching of the goſpell, cap. 3.1. For the lawe is excluded, and debarred in the matter of Iuſtification, faith onely ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving place, apprehending, and apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the imputed righteouſnes of Ieſus Chriſt. But the lawe in the matter of ſanctification is admitted as the rule to which the chriſtian ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould ſquare this converſation, and as the lanterne that ſhould lead him in the pathes of the Lords co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle inſiſteth in this purpoſe, from the beginning of the <hi>3</hi> chap. to the ſecond parte of this fift: and after that he hath throughly reaſoned, and in the end co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cluded in the laſt verſe of the chap: go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing before, that they were not the chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6780:4"/>
of the bondwoman <hi>Hagar,</hi> as <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael,</hi> that is ſervants, and ſlaues under the law through workes, and ſo lying under the curſe thereof, but ſonnes of the free woeman <hi>Sara,</hi> as <hi>Iſaac,</hi> that is, heires of the promiſe through faith in Ieſus; In theſe wordes, which we haue read, he inferreth, by way of a ſecond concluſion of the premiſes, a graue, &amp; powerfull admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ſeeing they were free, and freed from all the bonds &amp; bondage of the law morall, and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonial, their geeat care ſhould be to keepe themſelues ſo.</p>
            <p>The admonition hath 2 branches, The one an exhortation to ſtand faſt in the libertie; The other a dehortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the contrary, not to intangle &amp;c. Between theſe two is interlaced a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or argument to perſwade to the one, &amp; diſſwade from the other, taken from the purchaſer, and giver of this li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bertie, who is Chriſt, and ſo from the excellency thereof. This is the <hi>libertie</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:6780:4"/>
wherewith Chriſt hath made us free, therefore ſtand faſt in it: This is the <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> wherewith Chriſt hath made us free, therfore be not entangled againe with the yoke of bondage.</p>
            <p>In the exhortation we begin at this word (therefore) which is a particle of illation, relatiue of the laſt verſe of the chapt: going before; upon the which this whole admonition is inforced as a neceſſary conſequent, and by a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſary conſequent: <hi>we are the children of the free woeman Sara &amp;c. Let us ſtand faſt therfore in this liberty. We are not the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the ſervant, let us not therefore be entangled &amp;c. we are the children of the fre woman and not of the ſervant, let us ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d faſt in the liberty, wherwith Chriſt hath made us free, and be not entangled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine with the yoke of bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond word is <hi>(liberty).</hi> There are ſundry ſorts of <hi>liberty,</hi> a naturall <hi>liberty,</hi> a civill <hi>liberty,</hi> a bodily <hi>liberty,</hi> a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>liberty.</hi> The firſt three ſorts we over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6780:5"/>
as not pertinent to this text, and purpoſe. The <hi>liberty</hi> of which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaketh here is a ſupernatural, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, and a heavenly liberty, which is generally divided thus, into a ſpiritual internal <hi>liberty,</hi> and a ſpiritual external <hi>liberty.</hi> The internall <hi>liberty</hi> is the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, and gift of Chriſt to his owne children, whereby he ſetts them at fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome both in ſoule &amp; body, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, from the ſpirituall thraldome of ſinne, Sathan &amp;c: And this is twofold, the <hi>liberty</hi> of Iuſtification, and the <hi>liber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie</hi> of ſanctification. The <hi>liberty</hi> which juſtification brings conſiſteth in theſe poynts; in perfect freedom from ſinne both originall and actuall, in reſpect of meere imputation; <hi>Now ye are freed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne. Rom. 6.22.</hi> From the guiltines ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of; <hi>Who will lay any thing to the charge of Gods choſen? Rom. 8.33.</hi> From the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment thereof, death and condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>There is no condemnation to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which are in Chriſt Ieſus Rom 8.</hi>1. From the law
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6780:5"/>
morall, the revealer of ſinne &amp; death, in regard of the curſe, and condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it denounceth, the juſtification it propoſeth, the rigour of obedience it requyreth, <hi>ye are not under the law. Rom: 6:14. Ye are divided from the lawe.</hi> Rom: <hi>7:6. The lawe is not given to the righteous man,</hi> 1. Tim. 1.9. From the law ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall the witneſſer of ſinne; <hi>Chriſt hath put out the handwryting of Ordinances which was againſt us, toke it out of the way, faſtened it upon the Croſſe,</hi> Col. 2.24. and ſo from the traditions and precepts of men, or things indifferent whatſoever, as binding the conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the chriſtian <hi>liberty,</hi> or <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie.</hi> Rom. 14.16. <hi>Ye are bought with a price be not the ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of men.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.23.</p>
            <p>The <hi>liberty</hi> which ſanctification brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth is that ſpirituall priviledge, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Gods children are freed from the power and dominion of ſinne, Sathan &amp;c: not perfectly, but in parte, yet in al the powers, and faculties of the ſoules,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6780:6"/>
ſenſes, and members of the body: The minde from the power of darknes, the will from the power of diſobedience, the heart from the power of deadnes, the affections from the power of pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and corruption, the body and members thereof from the power of ſinne, wherby they are made weapons of unrighteouſnes: that the renued man thus freed, might, at the leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the inner man, delight in the lawe of God, and in his minde ſerue it without conſtraint, willingly, &amp; chear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully: <hi>The law of the ſpirit of life, which is in Chriſt Ieſus, hath freed me from the law</hi> (that is the power and authoritie) <hi>of ſinne and death, Rom: 8:2.</hi> This <hi>liberty</hi> of ſanctification hath two degrees, the one is in this life imperfect, which may be called the <hi>liberty</hi> of grace, the other after this life, perfect, the <hi>liberty</hi> of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, Rom: 8.21. <hi>the glorious libertie of the ſonnes of God.</hi> The ſame Apoſtle to the Col: 1.13. ſhutteth up this twofold li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6780:6"/>
of Iuſtification &amp; ſanctification in a word; <hi>The Father</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered us from the power of darknes, and hath tranſlated us into the kingdome of his deare ſonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now from this internall <hi>liberty</hi> follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth that comfortable <hi>liberty,</hi> which the Apoſtle in ſundry places calls <hi>(Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>êſia)</hi> wherby the ſoule of the freeman <hi>hath free acceſſe to the throne of grace, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue mercy, and finde grace to help in time of need.</hi> Heb: 4.16. From this ſpringeth that <hi>peace which paſſeth all underſtanding,</hi> Phil. 4.7. Rom. 5.1. That <hi>ioy</hi> which Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter calleth <hi>glorious &amp; unſpeakable,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.8. Without this internal liberty ther is nothing in the ſoule and conſcience of the ſinner but terrour, diſtraction, and doubting even in the ſmalleſt mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The externall <hi>liberty</hi> which is inſtru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mental, and defenſiue in reſpect of the former is likewiſe twofold; the <hi>libertie</hi> of the preaching and profeſſing of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6780:7"/>
truth of God, the true doctrin drawne out of the pure fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine of the word; The <hi>libertie</hi> of the practiſe of holy Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline following from the ſame foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: This may be called the <hi>liberty</hi> of the houſe of God, wherby it is gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which is the <hi>Church of the living God, the piller and ground of the truth.</hi> 1. Tim: <hi>3.</hi>15. We call them inſtrumental, becauſe they are Gods powerfull, and ordinary inſtruments, through which by his ſpirit he worketh the internall <hi>liberty,</hi> continueth, &amp; keepeth it. Take away theſe inſtruments, no Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, no ſanctification. 1. Pet. 1.23. We call them dcfenſiue, becauſe the gard the inward, which if they were not, would eaſily vaniſh, and Satan would ſoone weare it out of the ſoule.</p>
            <p>The third word in this exhortation is, that he deſireth to <hi>(ſtand) in this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty,</hi> yea to ſtand faſt (as the word im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth) as within a <hi>compaſſe, or ſtation.</hi> There appeareth to be a <hi>Metaphore</hi> in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6780:7"/>
the word, borrowed from the cuſtome of worldly warriours, who ſtand ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt in the ſtation in the which their captaine placeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, reſolved without feare to fight, never to flee, but coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly to confront their adverſaries. So <hi>ſtand ye ſtedfaſt</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) and ſettle the affection of your heart faſt in the <hi>liberty,</hi> wherin, as in a ſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, your graue, &amp; gracious captaine <hi>Ieſus</hi> hath placed you, reſiſting by faith that ſpirituall adverſary the Devil, who wil ſtriue by all meanes poſſible to drawe you out of that liberty. This is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in the which the Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eth the internall <hi>libertie</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the law morall, ceremoniall, ſin, death &amp;c. In the afore ſaid reſpects, and by conſequence of this, we inferr the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall defenſiue liberties. For if we ſhould ſtand faſt in one poynt of this ſpirituall <hi>liberty,</hi> then we ſhould ſtand faſt in all.</p>
            <p>The dehortation is from the contrary.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6780:8"/>
               <hi>Be not entangled &amp;c:</hi> The <hi>yoke of bondage</hi> is oppoſed <hi>as</hi> contrary to <hi>liberty; the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gling with this yoke</hi> to the ſtanding in the <hi>libertie.</hi> This <hi>bondage</hi> is a ſpirituall bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage of the ſoule, &amp; conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally, and is anſwerable in the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to this libertie in all the ſorts, &amp; poynts thereof, the <hi>bondage</hi> under ſin, Sathan, death, the law morall, ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall, traditions of men, Antichriſt the man of ſinne in corrupt doctrine, and Diſcipline. We briefly paſſe it over, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is cleere by the contrary in the words, <hi>be not entangled.</hi> And now there appeares alſo to be a <hi>metaphore</hi> borrow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed from the cuſtom of Oxen, or other beaſts, whoſe neckes being once com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended or conteyned (as the word ſignifieth) in the yoke, are forced to follow whitherſoever the driver by word, or by goad luſteth. So, faith the Apoſtle, if you fall backe to <hi>bondage,</hi> you entangle your ſelues with ſuch a heavie yoke that whither ſoever ſinne,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6780:8"/>
or Sathan leades you, you muſt goe.</p>
            <p>This word <hi>(agayne)</hi> importeth not, that the Galatians had been under the Ceremoniall law; for they were of the Gentills, and not Iewes, to whom this law was proper; but that they had ben before under the yoke of bondage, the law moral, engraven in their hearts by nature, albeit defaced by ſin, the yoke of ſinne, Idolatrie, &amp;c. So that, now to fall backe to this <hi>bondage,</hi> or whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpirituall <hi>yoke,</hi> was to be <hi>entangled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the dehortation; in which the Apoſtle expreſly meaneth the <hi>yoke</hi> of the law ceremoniall, &amp; morall; But by conſequence all ſpirituall <hi>yokes</hi> of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage whatſoever are forbidden; for if we ſhould not entangle our ſelues in a my, then likewiſe in none.</p>
            <p>The reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enterlaced betwixt the two branches of the admonition is drawne from the purchaſer, and giver, and ſo the excellencie of this <hi>libertie,</hi> which is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6780:9"/>
ſo much the more excellent, by how much the contrary <hi>bondage</hi> is dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. If ye aske who is the purchaſer &amp; giver of this libertie: the Apoſtle Paul anſwereth here, it is <hi>Chriſt. If the Sonne ſhall make yow free, ye ſhalbe free in deed,</hi> ſaith Chriſt himſelfe of himſelfe, Ioh: 8.38. If the Father be the author of this libertie, the ſonne is the purchaſer and giver of this libertie, the ſpirit is the worker, and ſealer up of this liberty in our ſoules. If ye aske whereby Chriſt hath purchaſed this libertie, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Peter</hi> anſwereth, <hi>Not with corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thinges as ſilver, or gold, but with the pretious bloud of Chriſt, as of a Lambe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled, and without ſpotte.</hi> 1 Pet: 1.18.19. If ye aske, which is the regiſter, or <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter</hi> of this libertie, in and by the which our right of this liberty is ſett downe, and made ſure; we anſwer; The word of the Old, and New Teſtament, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally the word of the Evangeliſts, in the which this liberty, &amp; all the ſorts,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6780:9"/>
and particuler poynts therof are plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and plentifully layd out before our eyes. <hi>The word is truth: if ye know the truth, the truth ſhall make you free,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, Iohn 8.23. For it is both the Charter, and working inſtrument of this <hi>liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the meaning of this whole ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition is this ſhortly and ſimplie: Seing ye are once ſet at liberty, and ſo freed from ſpirituall thraldome, by <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> the Lord of life and <hi>liberty,</hi> ſtand faſt to this libertie, and fall not backe againe under the wofull miſery of any ſpirituall <hi>bondage</hi> whatſoever. To come to the doctrine. Firſt we ſee, there is a <hi>libertie</hi> wherewith the Sonne of God hath priviledged his people, whom <hi>Peter</hi> calleth <hi>the people ſet at liber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie,</hi> 1 Pet: 2.9. which is heavenly, ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, and ſupernaturall, and in nature far differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t from any earthly, or world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly libertie: which is, even in all, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of the ſorts and poynts ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6780:10"/>
the purchaſe of his owne pretious bloud, the free gift of his liberall loue, the right wherof is conferred to them by the charter of his bleſſed word, ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led up in the tables of their hearts and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces by the ſpirit of grace, which is delivered to us from day to day by the publicke preaching of the word. Therfore neither Angell in heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor man on earth ſhould take upon them to chop, or change, in this liberty, or the meaneſt poynt therof, without the warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the word; unles they would that the purchaſer of this libertie ſhould be avenged of them for the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olation thereof. It is true, in outward or earthly liberties given by men, or which are amonge men for outward ſociety, or comodity, men may doe as they think meet, alter, add, impare &amp;c. But as for this liberty, and the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars therof, which come, as it were, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately out of the hands of Chriſt, let men take heed how they meddle
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6780:10"/>
with them, to add, to alter, to impaire, or to pervert, as they would wiſh that God ſhould not meddle with them in wrath. Yet ſuch is the follie, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of mortall men, that they haue oft their head, and their hand in theſe inviolable liberties, altering, or diſanulling the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their owne further libertie, or rather looſnes to the fleſh. Take an exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple from the Papiſts, who in effect overthrow this liberty in all and every poynt thereof; The libertie of Iuſtification and ſanctification by their freewill in nature, their prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to Iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, their good works chiefly of the outward man, their pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimages, purgatory, and ſatisfactions, by the which they entangle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with the yoke of the law, ſin, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation; the libertie of thinges in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different or humane traditions, by an heap of Idolatrous, &amp; ſuperfluous Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, thruſt upon the conſciences of ignorant people, as a parte of Gods
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6780:11"/>
worſhip neceſſary, and meritorious; The defenſiue liberties by their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written verities, and traditions, mixed &amp; matched with the pure, and ſincere word of truth; by their Antichriſtian Hierarchy, and innumerable ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious rites, defeating, yea excluding the true Diſcipline, and comely order of the houſe of God. Thus while they ſhew themſelues enimies to this liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in all the particulars of it, they alſo declare that all the linckes of this ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall yoke of bondage lie heavie upon the necke of their ſoules, which is a juſt and deſerved recompence of the violation of this <hi>liberty, wherwith Chriſt hath made us free.</hi> Therfore by their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample we ſhould beware of ſuch: for we haue great cauſe, ſeing within thes few yeares (it may be, perceiving that we were inclyning their way in our Church goverme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t) they are ſo encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp; encouraged, that not onely here they ſet up their heades, but alſo they
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6780:11"/>
haue been bold (as yow know of late) to ſet out the publicke enſignes of Ido<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latry, as though their had been neither Prince, nor Paſtor in Iſrael; as though both the edge of the civill and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſword had been either broken or blunted; and yet they are not much daſhed, nor diſmayed. As for us (my brethren) it becommeth us alwayes in holines, and faithfulnes to preſerue, &amp; mainteine every one of theſe liberties, ſo farr forth as our place, or power will extend, that we may <hi>ſtand faſt</hi> in them, ſeeing Chriſt by them hath made us free, that <hi>we be not entangled againe with the yoke of bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly the Apoſtle ſheweth that this happie priviledge, which Chriſt hath purchaſed for us, is not a looſnes, but a <hi>libertie;</hi> not a looſnes, or a licence to ſinne, but a libertie in holines, and righteouſnes to ſerue the Lord; not a looſenes, or a looſe rayne to ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſoever our vayne, and raging luſts
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6780:12"/>
leade us, but a libertie which is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wieſ a yoke; not like the yoke of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage which is hard, and heavie, a yoke of iron, but a golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yoke, of the which our Saviour Chriſt Math: 11.30. ſaith, <hi>My yoke is eaſie, and my burden light;</hi> not a looſenes that hath no limittes, but a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie which is bounded, and limitted by the Lord himſelfe in his bleſſed word; which we ſhall eaſily perceiue by paſſing through ſhortly the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culers of this libertie. Firſt the liberty of Iuſtification, &amp; ſanctification is not a looſnes, that they who imagine they injoy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may doe what they luſt, but a liberty <hi>which ſhould not be abuſed as an occaſion to the fleſh</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle in this ſame chapter 13: which hath his owne limitts preſcribed by God in his word; <hi>Being made free from ſinne, yea are made the ſervants of righteouſnes.</hi> Rom: 6.18. <hi>Being freed from ſinne, ye are made ſervants unto God, having your fruite in holines, Rom: 6:22.</hi> There is a limitte of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6780:12"/>
this liberty; righteouſnes, holines, or the ſervice of God. <hi>Ye are a people ſet at liberty, that ye ſhould ſhew forth the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of him, who hath called you out of dark<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes into his marveilous light. 1. Pet: 2.9.</hi> There is another limitte of this liberty further; The freedome from the lawe is not a looſenes, as though we might caſt the law of God behind our backs, as no way perteyning to us; but a liber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty limitted. For albeit we be freed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the curſe and condemnation of it, yet are we not ſimply freed from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of it: Albeit we be freed from the correction of it, yet not from the direction of it: It continueth to be a di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rector, and leader of us in the way of light. Oh how far then are the <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> and <hi>Epicures</hi> of this age blynded, (who are ſo in effect, albeit lurking under the ſhadow of outward profeſſion) with all the <hi>Hypocrites</hi> in theſe dayes; they (reſting themſelues upon the broken reed of a blynde conceit, that they are
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6780:13"/>
partakers of this <hi>liberty</hi>) caſt of the law, holines, righteouſnes, and all, under covert, following, &amp; fulfilling the luſts. and vanityes of a prophane heart, as though it were a looſenes, or licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, and not a holy and a happy <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</hi> Agayne <hi>libertie</hi> in thinges indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, as in meat, drincke, apparell &amp;c: is not a looſenes, but a liberty limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. The Argument of the bellygods, glutto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; vayne glorious is not good, who reaſon thus; Meat, drincke, appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell are things indifferent, therefore I may eate, and drincke, when, and how oft, and how much ſoever I liſt, albeit exceſſively; I may weare what apparel I pleaſe, albeit never ſo coſtly, or glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. For ſo thou turneſt this <hi>liberty</hi> to a meere looſnes. To the which the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Paul</hi> ſetteth generally the limitts of order, comelines, aedification, and that mutuall charitie which ſhould be in chriſtian ſociety. Againe the <hi>libertie</hi> of preaching, and profeſſing the truth of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6780:13"/>
Gods word, is not a looſenes, ſo that a man may preach, or profeſſe what he pleaſeth, taking to himſelfe a liberty of conſcience (that ſo many wiſheth:) but it is a limitted liberty. We muſt preach the word, keeping our ſelues preciſely within the compaſſe therof; yea we muſt preach the word, <hi>as the word;</hi> there is a limitation both in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and manner. Likwiſe your profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt be, both in matter &amp; manner, as the word preſcribs. Laſtly, the <hi>liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of the government, &amp; Diſcipline of Gods houſe is not a looſnes, as though me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might ſet downe what forme ther of they pleaſed, but a <hi>libertie</hi> which is bounded, &amp; limitted, both in reſpect of the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiall poynts therof, which are fixed and immoveable, and the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantiall poynts therof, which are variable and changable. For the firſt, the limitts of the poynts fubſtantiall is the word, either expreſſe for the moſt parte, or at leaſt by neceſſary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6780:14"/>
the word, I ſay, particularly for every one of them; as the office bearers in the Church, their ſorts, degrees, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, power, offices, calling thereto, diſcharge thereof in preaching the word, adminiſtring the ſacraments, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing of Diſcipline; as is evident out of the Epiſtles of <hi>Paul,</hi> and the reſt. Therfore that is not a good argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, this or that, (as the eſtate of Biſhops humane, or ſuch other) is not againſt the word; there is nothing in the word againſt it; therefore it is lawfull. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it were ſo, that it were not againſt the word, yet it will not follow, if it be among the ſubſtantiall poynts, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning any office bearer, his office, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or ſuch like, which are perefct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; expreſly ſet downe in the word. But rather by the contrary it will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, by a ſure conſequence: It is not with the word, the word is not with it; therefore it is not lawfull. Otherwiſe this libertie is turned to looſenes. For
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6780:14"/>
the ſecond, the limitts of the poynts circumſtantiall, and ceremoniall, is like<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe by the word, but generally, bouu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding all, and every one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their uſe, with the foreſayd three limitts, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, comlines, and aedification. Where Ceremonies are placed in a Church, having theſe three joyned with them in peace, and wiſdome, let them be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned without ſuperſtition. Where Ceremonies are placed in a Church, breaking their bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, bringing in with them for order confuſion, for decency uncomely and vngraue diſguyzing, for aedification offence of the weake in faith (of whom there hath ben ever, and wilbe a number in the Church of Chriſt in all ages) and confirming of o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers in their ſuperſtitions; let them, without contention, in wiſdome and authority be removed; otherwiſe this <hi>liberty</hi> is turned into looſenes.</p>
            <p>Therfore this is not a good argument; all ceremonies are in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6780:15"/>
therefore they may be reteyned, or removed, placed, or diſplaced, accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to our pleaſure. It followeth not, becauſe there is a difference betwixt the indifferency of the thing indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in it ſelfe, and the indifferency of the uſe thereof: the thing indifferent in it ſelfe, and it owne nature (being nether inclyning to good, nor evil,) is, and abideth alwayes indifferent (the Chriſtian liberty thereof being in the conſcience as a benefite chiefly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning therto) the authority of man, yea of Angels is not able to alter, or change the nature thereof, by turning indifferency into neceſſitie; for this is onely proper to God to change the quality of thinges by the power of his precept. But the uſe of the thing indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent is, and abydes not alwayes and at al times indifferent, in reſpect of the accidents that accompany the ſame; ſometimes offence, uncomelines, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order following theron, which taketh
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6780:15"/>
away the indifferency of the uſe, byn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, &amp; reſtrayning the exrernall work that it be not done, albeit nothing tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching the internall liberty of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which is ever free; Otherwiſe the abuſe of the thing indifferent com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth in, of neceſſity craving reformati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on thereof. Somtimes againe the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full authority of men, in a diſcrete co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement or precept of Chriſtian charity, accompanieth the ſame, injoy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning the uſe of the thing indifferent; &amp; ſo obliging, and bynding the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall worke to be done, (although not the internall liberty and conſcience) and that not abſolutely, but in caſe of ſcandall; otherwiſe the worke without ſinne may be omitted.</p>
            <p>If ye will ſay the law giver, by his ſuperiour power, concerning the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall uſe of the thing indifferent, will remoue the offence followinge therein; It will not, but rather aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate it, becauſe thereby the externall
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6780:16"/>
worke appeareth to be bound to the offenſiue uſe of the thing indifferent, which before was free. If ye will aske whether the ſuperiour power may not by preceept injoyne the uſe of thinges indifferent; I anſwer yea, but with theſe conditions: Firſt that it be without the opinion of merit, and neceſſary Divine worſhip; Secondly, that it be without the offence of the weake, or any of Gods children what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, and the ſtrenghthening the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious in their blynd errors; Third<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, that it be not impoſed with the clauſe of perpetuity, as though it were a thing neceſſary; but that it be left al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable, according as the circumſtance of time, place, &amp; perſon ſhall requyre; Fourthly, that it be not urged under the puniſhment of neceſſity. For exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, if a law, or Injunction ſhould im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the uſe of the ſurplice in time of divine ſervice, the ring in mariage &amp;c: under the payne of depoſition, this is
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6780:16"/>
to make the uſe of a thing indifferent neceſſary, for what other or greater ſhalbe the puniſhment of fornication, drunkenes &amp;c: in the perſon of any ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rituall office bearer. So then of all this ye ſee, what a gratious <hi>liberty it is, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Chriſt hath made us free;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how ſtedfaſtly we ſhould <hi>ſtand in it,</hi> not with a looſe, &amp; licentious heart, but with affections faſt ſetled by faith thereon, <hi>that we be not entangled agayne with the yoke of bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Apoſtle layeth out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes the dolefull miſery, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in they inwrappe themſelues, who for ſake this <hi>liberty;</hi> they <hi>entangle</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with the fearefull <hi>yoke of bondage.</hi> There is no meane between theſe two; but of neceſſity he that <hi>ſtandeth not in this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie liberty,</hi> muſt be <hi>entangled with that un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>happie yoke of bondage.</hi> When we fall from the one, we fall into the other, when we declyne from the one, we in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clyne to the other. But this agayne
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6780:17"/>
doubleth the miſery. For if it were but the firſt yoke, and the firſt time therof, it were ſo much the more tolerable; But to be once yoked, and freed, and after freedom to be yoked againe, that is commonly a remediles yoke, which is never removed: the laſt condition of that man is worſe then the firſt. For when, in the firſt bondage, onely one unclea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e ſpirit poſſeſſed the houſe, that is the hart; in the ſecond, ſeaven worſe then the firſt enters in, &amp; takes poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Wher the firſt yoke was but ſingle, the ſecond ſhalbe ſeavenfold, bynding the heart ſo faſt, that it can hardly ever returne agayne to liberty. For albeit there may be a yoke, &amp; a yoke againe, yet ſeldom falleth it out, that there is a liberty, and a liberty agayne. Many haue been once yoked, and after freed, (albeit not effectually) and yet yoked agayne; but few once freed, and after yoked, are freed agayne. Beſides that parable cited before out of Math: 12:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6780:17"/>
the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> likewiſe cleares, and confirmes this poynt. 2 Pet. 2.20. <hi>Yf once after they haue eſcaped from the filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the world, through the acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Lord &amp; Saviour Ieſus Chriſt, they are yet intangled againe therein, and overcome, the latter end is worſe with them then the beginning; for it had been better for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not to haue knowne the way of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, then after they haue knowne it, to turne from the holy commandement given unto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As this is true of the yoke of ſinne, ſo is it true of the yoke particularly mentioned in this text, and of every particular <hi>yoke of bondage</hi> whatſoever. Now as concernyng us, that may be ſayd, which the Apoſtle ſaith of the <hi>Epheſians</hi> chap: 5.8. <hi>We were once darknes, but now we are light in the Lord;</hi> we were once under the heavy yoke of bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage, both of ſinne, and of the man of ſinne; but now we are, and haue been ſet at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iberty, principally from the bondage
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6780:18"/>
of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> his darkened, and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted doctrine, and Diſcipline; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore carefull ſhould we be <hi>to walke in that light and liberty, and ſtand faſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that we be not entangled agayne</hi> with the yoke of bondage, and ſo our dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes be doubled, our yoke ſeaven fold ſtrengthened, and that proverbe tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned even upon us, <hi>The dog is returned to his owne vomit, and the Sow, which was waſhed, to the wallowing in the myre. 2:</hi> Peter 2:22.</p>
            <p>Yf any will ſay we need not to be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayd or ſuch yokes, they are far from us in this land, we are in no da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger: wel, if it be ſo, we thanke the Lord; if other<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe, we pray him to ridd us fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. Onely this we ſay, that the ſpirituall yokes of bondage uſe to come ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and ſlyding in very ſubtilly, and ſecretly, under the ſhadow, and cover of many fayre prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes. For evill, in the beginning &amp; firſt entry, is ever almoſt in a myſtery hid up. And this is the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6780:18"/>
craft of Satan, who, when he hath any worke of weight to doe, <hi>can transforme himſelfe, and his inſtruments, into Angels of light.</hi> Dolefull experience in times paſt teacheth this, in the birth and growth of <hi>Antichriſt the man of ſinne,</hi> which the Apoſtle calleth 2. Theſ: 2.7. <hi>the myſtery of iniquity, which doth already worke.</hi> Behold the entry, and creeping in of this yoke was evill, even in the dayes of the Apoſtle; the firſt degree and ſtep whereof is little different fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our new moderators. It was not very ſenſible, or appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: upon which while this man of ſinne ſtood, he appeared little higher then the reſt, but ſtood e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall with them upon the earth: yet by progreſſe of time, ſincerity and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility paſſing away, covetouſnes, and ambition previaling, he did climbe up ſtep after ſtep, from this to Biſhop, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Biſhop to Archbiſhop, from Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop to Patriach, from Patriarch to Pope, till he came to the top of this
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6780:19"/>
his pinnacle, upon the which he ſtands now in his Antichriſtian greatnes. Deſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cend he will not the way he aſcended, becauſe he is the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinne, appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for perdition. It reſteth there; for that Sathan (who carried him up) in Gods righteous judgment, and in his appoynted time, ſhall throwe him downe, and ridde the Church of him. Therfore it is very requyſit that Gods people, (but principally the Paſtors of his people to whom the cuſtody and chiefe care of this <hi>liberty</hi> is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) be very wiſe, that nothing, nether perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor pollicy, enter into the houſe of God, without a narrow triall, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myning, and ſifting every thing exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that under faire colours, the ſubtill ſerpent ſlyde not into the paradice of God, to enſnare, and deceiue ſimple <hi>Eva.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was not for nought, that Chriſt himſelfe, the purchaſer of this liberty, recommendeth to his Diſciples, <hi>Math.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6780:19"/>
10:16. the wiſdome of the Serpent,</hi> that the old Serpent in his inſtruments ſhould not beguyle them, <hi>and the ſimplicitie and innocencie of the Doue,</hi> that the mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſnes of that enemy, who was <hi>a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſlayer from the beginning,</hi> ſhould not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome them. Our Maſter and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our joynes and mixes theſe two ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues togither; becauſe the Serpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome not ſanctified and marſhalled with the Doues ſimplicity, will make but an <hi>Achitophel,</hi> or a <hi>Matchiavel;</hi> and the Doues ſimplicity, not ſanctified &amp; accompanyed with the Serpents wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, will make up but a ſilly and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable childiſhnes. Therefore he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendeth to them, &amp; to al his owne, to the end of the world (eſpecially his ſervants in the miniſtery) an holy wiſe ſimplicity, &amp; a holy ſimple wiſedome; that without malice and deceit they may diſcharge the duties of their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; ſuffering nothing to enter into the houſe of God, prejudiciall to this
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6780:20"/>
liberty, or to any ſort or poynt therof: neyther hyding up any ſuch thing, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the collours or clokes of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, which the Apoſtle Paul <hi>2. Cor. 4.2.</hi> calleth <hi>the clokes of ſhame,</hi> and the carryer of them <hi>a walker in craftines:</hi> the clokes of ſhame, becauſe the cover a ſhamefull and diſhoneſt body; that is, plottes, and purpoſes, which if they were ſeene in their owne colours, the very authors and inventors of them would be aſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ed of them: ſuch clokes beſeeme not the Miniſters of God; &amp; the Apoſtle in that ſame place, for his owne parte, renounceth ſuch. They ſhould be cladd with holines, wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, ſimplicity, ſincerity, making their very hearts and mindes, in all the workes of their callings ſeene ſenſible, &amp; approu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the world, and walking even as though every one ſaw their heart as well as their hand, in reſpect of their ſyncerity, and were witnes to their minde, as well as to their mouth. To
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6780:20"/>
this ſhould be our ſtudie and endevor, that ſo we might <hi>ſtand faſt in that liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, wherewith Chriſt hath made us free, and not entangle our ſelues agayne with any yoke of bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly the Apoſtle telleth vs, that there is no keeping nor continuyng in this liberty, unles we <hi>ſtand faſt ſetled,</hi> &amp; our affections faſtened thereon: this is the principall meanes, whereby we may keep this liberty. For ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tymes, as the word importeth, there wilbe ſo many mighty adverſaryes, ſpirituall &amp; temporall, ſo many ſtrong temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, both of terrors and allurements drawing and dragging at this liberty, to pull it from us, that they will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, unles we with all the powers of our ſoules, and all the ſtrenght of our hearts, renewed by the mighty force of the grace of the ſpirit of Ieſus, <hi>hold faſt our hold.</hi> It is the looſe holding of this liberty that looſeth it: It is the faſt and ſure holding of it, that is the great and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6780:21"/>
preſerver thereof. He that ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in this liberty ſtaggering, or hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any one foote up, ready to ſtep out of it, if occaſion doe preſent either perill, or preferment, and profit, he (I ſay) wilbe eaſily beaten from this liber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty. But he who fixeth and faſteneth both his feet, his minde, and his heart theron, wil abide the brunt, and batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt temptation, and yet keep his ſtanding.</p>
            <p>Now, to ſtrengthen us to ſtand faſt, there are two thinges principally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyred, <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Loue:</hi> Faith wherby we ſhould be perſwaded of this liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, &amp; of all the ſorts, poynts, &amp; bounds thereof, as purchaſed by the bloud of Ieſus, &amp; regiſtred in the word of God; the want wherof, or of that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>venient meaſure thereof that is requiſite for this aſſurance, maketh us looſe our ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. For the leaſt te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptation, that ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth upon a man of an vnſtable minde, that is ſtaggeri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; wavering through
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6780:21"/>
doubt, will drawe him away from this <hi>liberty.</hi> If we begin once to doubt of our Diſcipline, or Church-goverme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, whether it be ſtabliſhed by the ſure warrant of the word, or whether it be a thing alterable and indifferent, and that another forme may be lawfully re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceived, (and many now a dayes thinke ſo, who would make their gayne by ſuch a change) then our <hi>ſtedfaſtnes</hi> is gone, and we eaſily are drawne away by any occaſions.</p>
            <p>Agayne, the unfayned loue to this <hi>liberty</hi> maketh our <hi>ſtanding</hi> ſteedfaſt. Loth would they be to turne from it, or the leaſt poynt thereof, who loue it well. But if loue be lacking, or that con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>venient meaſure therof that is reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, there wilbe little, or no ſtanding to this liberty. But what is the requiſit meaſure of this loue? To loue this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty better then all outward or earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thinges, yea better then our life it ſelfe. When we preferre theſe earthly
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6780:22"/>
thinges, as profit, or preferment &amp;c. in this world, and giue to them firſt and chiefe place in our affections, then we want this loue, &amp; ſo looſe our <hi>ſtanding.</hi> A man that loveth honor and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie, better then this liberty, to winne a poynt of this worldly profit, or preferment, will looſe a poynt of this liberty, yea two, ere he will want it. <hi>Demas,</hi> of whom <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Phil: 2.4. that he was one of his fellow helpers,</hi> in <hi>2: Tim: 4.10.</hi> he ſaith crying out by way of complaynt, <hi>Demas hath forſaken me.</hi> Well, there then is a token of <hi>Demas</hi> his looſe ſtanding: but what was the cauſe of it? <hi>Paul</hi> addeth it (<hi>and hath em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced this preſent world,</hi> ſaith he.) A ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſible ſigne he loved the world better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Miniſtery and this moved him to forſake the libertie of his ſpirituall calling, when he ſaw the occaſion of worldly profitt and preferment. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if <hi>Demas</hi> heart be bent to imbrace the world, loving it better then his
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6780:22"/>
Miniſtery, it is meete he ſhould even forſake <hi>Paul,</hi> and betake him to the thing he loveth beſt, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to hold the Miniſtery with the one hand, and grype the world with theother; for theſe two grypes agree not well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the one looſeth ever the other.</p>
            <p>If any will alleadge that the earthly prerogatiues in a Miniſter get to him, in his Miniſtery, credit, reverence, and authority; the Apoſtle 2. Cor. 10.4. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth: <hi>The weapons of our warfare are not carnall, nor earthly,</hi> whereby we pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe and gett hearts in faith and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> in loue and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to our ſelues and our Miniſtery in him; <hi>but ſpirituall, and mightie in God</hi> to this effect. They are grace, fidelity, ſincerity, godlines in a Miniſter which are the meanes of his advancement in the hearts of the faithfull. I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that we carrie more credit, and are better accounted of, in the hearts of thoſe that feare the Lord, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6780:23"/>
our ſelues (within the compaſſe of our calling) with the ſtyles of <hi>M: George, M. Iohn, Paſtor of ſuch, or ſuch a place,</hi> then, when we borrow, through ambition, the titles of worldly honor, and dignityes, loving the ſtyle of my <hi>Lord Biſhop</hi> better, then to be called a faithfull and diligent Miniſter. So we ſee how needfull it is, that we ſhould ſtudy to gett faith, and growe in it, whereby we may be perſwaded in all the poynts of our liberty, and calling; and alſo to gett loue, and growe in it, whereby we may hold faſt, that ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be drawne from us, nor we fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, but that <hi>we may ſtand faſt in the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty &amp;c:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſurely, yf we ſhould enter into a reckonyng of the reaſons, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that ſhould moue us to <hi>ſtand,</hi> it would requyre a longer time, then is allowed to us. Therefore we ſhall only bring out a few. 1. This liberty, in all the poynts of it, is the purchaſe of the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6780:23"/>
pretious bloud of <hi>Ieſus.</hi> It is deere bought, the price is great, the worth is great, &amp; ſuch things (albeit earthly) we uſe to keep well: <hi>ſhould not we then ſtand faſt in this liberty?</hi> 2. This liberty is the free gift of <hi>Chriſts</hi> liberall loue. Now, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he gift uſeth to be liked, and kept, if it were but for the givers ſake: <hi>Should not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e then ſtand faſt in this liberty? 3.</hi> The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight of this liberty is made, and given vnto us in the ſure charter of the word of God; regiſtred in the bookes of the Old and New Teſtament: there ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be under the heavens a ſurer holding: <hi>ſhould we not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtand faſt in this liberty? 4.</hi> (Which toucheth principally the defenſiue liberties) we haue them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, and ratified by the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall lawes of our Country: <hi>ſhould we not then ſtand faſt in them?</hi> 5. We haue ben many yeares in peaceable poſſeſſion of them. Now, we know that the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſociety in the land wilbe loth to looſe the leaſt poynt of their civill li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6780:24"/>
having both right to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (and the ſame ratified by the <hi>Actes of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament</hi>) &amp; poſſeſſion of them: yea they will admit no endeavour or attempt, that may prejudice a circumſtance of them, much leſſe the ſubſtance. <hi>Should we not then ſtand faſt in this liberty,</hi> to the which we haue right from God, regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in his word, ratified by the lawes of the land, ſo long by us peacably poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed?</p>
            <p n="6">6. To theſe liberties, all eſtates of the land, <hi>King, Counſell, Nobility, Paſtors, People,</hi> haue ſworne, and ſubſcribed. Sworne? Looke the <hi>Confeſsion of faith.</hi> Wherby? <hi>By the great name of the Lord our God.</hi> Whereto? <hi>To continue in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Doctrine, and Diſcipline of this reformed Church, and to defend the ſame.</hi> How long? <hi>All the dayes of our liues.</hi> Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what payne? <hi>Vnder the payne contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the law, and danger both of body and ſoule, in the day of Gods fearefull iudgment.</hi> How haue all ſworne and ſubſcribed?
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6780:24"/>
Not ſecretly, but ſolemnely; agayne, not ignorantly, or raſhly, but (ſaith the wordes) <hi>after long and due examination, being perſwaded in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience through know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge wrought by the holy ſpirit, and not moved for worldly reſpects, in a through reſolution, willingly beleeving, confeſsing, ſubſcribing, affirming before God, and the whole world, that it is the onely true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, pleaſing God, and bringing ſalvation to man, and promiſing to mainteine it both in the Doctrine, and Diſcipline.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that if any will alledge that now they may alter, becauſe they ſee grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter light: ſurely it may well be, greater livyng thou ſeeſt, but greater light thou canſt not ſee, to make thee alter. This is a ſtrong reaſon to bynde the looſeſt heart, and make ſtedfaſt the moſt wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dring ſoule; unles in the ſight of God, his Angels, and the world, we would be manifeſtly perjured, &amp; make open <hi>Apoſtaſy,</hi> to the high blaſpheming of that Goſpell of grace, which we
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6780:25"/>
preach and profeſſe. 7. And laſtly, we know not how long our God ſhal gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to vs the liberty of this preſent life. If, while we enjoye it, we likewiſe keep faſt this pretious liberty purchaſed to us by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſo long poſſeſſed of vs in peace, the certeinly, in weale, in wo, in life, in death, we ſhall find the fruit and comfort thereof. But if we forſake this liberty, and God come and cut of the liberty of this preſent life; with what aſſurance ſhall we looke for the <hi>liberty</hi> of that better life. Therefore <hi>let us ſtand faſt in the liberty wherwith Chriſt hath made us free, and not be entangled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne with the yoke of bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, it may be that ſome wilbe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonyng within themſelues after this manner. What needes all this a-doe of this liberty, the keeping of it, and ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in it? Wherein is it hurt? And by whom? I anſwer to the firſt. If ye will compare the ſtate of our Church, as it was within theſe few yeares, with that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6780:25"/>
which now is, the graces and faces of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aithfull men zealous for the houſe of God, their vnity, and amity, the order &amp; comelines of their meetings, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the Lords worke which the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was, with that which now we looke vpon with our eyes, diſorder, confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; diviſion, your queſtion wil eaſily be reſolved. The time hath been, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our Church &amp; liberties haue been as a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſed cittie or houſe, but now doores and windowes are partly caſt open, partly broken up, &amp; enemies entered, ſo that the faithfull keepers wilbe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, eyther to yeld, or to ſuffer: but to ſuffer is farr better, for if either our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, through craft, be undermined, or through reward be given out of our handes, it is likely the Lord will never honor us with them agayne. But if by violence they be throwne out of our hands, then poſſeſſe we a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, &amp;, in our Gods great mercy, they ſhalbe repoſſeſſed, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he thinks time.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6780:26"/>
Was not the glorious liberty of Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine and Diſcipline, exerciſed in this land, ſometime to it, that, which the
<hi>Arke of God was to Iſrael; the glory, and prayſe of it?</hi> which now is departing, &amp; there is none <hi>(like Phinehas wife)</hi> to mourne for it. Was not Scotland, albe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>it the meaneſt among many Nations, yet renowned through the world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt, in his Goſpell of grace, was ſo clearely borne out before our eyes in it? And, as <hi>Bethleem Ephrathah, albeit litle among the thouſands of Iuda, yet renowned, becauſe Ieſus was borne in it?</hi> But now we are beating him downe, putting him in ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, covering his face as though we were of purpoſe now to bury him agayne with the Iewes. The Lord be mercifull to us: I need not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in theſe thinges, which are more then evident, whereof every one of us talketh privily, albeit we ſpeake no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much of them publikely.</p>
            <p>I anſwer to the ſecond queſtion, that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:6780:26"/>
is, by whom our liberties are hurt? As concerning our Soveraigne, the Kings Majeſtie, he promiſed at his departure out of this Country, and proteſted (as we heare) at that meeting late at <hi>Lieth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oe</hi> by his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioner, that it was no way his highnes intention, to alter our government, or to hurt our liberties. And to teſtifie our entier, and ſincere loue, reverence, and dutifull obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to him, we preach with Chriſt, Math: 22.21: <hi>Giue unto Caeſar</hi> (our chriſtian <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar) that which is his, and unto God, thoſe things which are his.</hi> With <hi>Paul Rom:</hi> 13.1. <hi>Let every ſoule be ſubiect unto the higher power, which is of God, and ordayned by him.</hi> With Peter 1. Pet: 2:17. <hi>Feare God, honor the King.</hi> We pray for him, that his throne may be eſtabliſhed with the Sunne, and the Moone, in his owne perſon, and Royall ofspring, till the Sonne of God ſett downe his throne in the cloudes, to judge the quicke, &amp; the dead. And we will giue to him
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6780:27"/>
more honor, then <hi>Saule</hi> requyred of <hi>Samuel,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he deſired, that he would <hi>but honor him before his people</hi> 1. Sam. 15.30. Not only wil we honor him before his people, but alſo before the Lord in ſincerity.</p>
            <p>Well then, let us ſearch out this hurt among our ſelues. The Lord hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted us to be <hi>the lightes of the land,</hi> holding out his light, before this dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened generation: to be the eyes for the body of his Church, to guide her forward in the way of grace; but we haue been, in a great meaſure, blinde, and darknes our ſelues. The Lord ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted us, to be <hi>the watchmen, ſet on the walles of his Sion to ſee, foreſee, blowe the trumpet, and giue warning</hi> to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in time of danger: but we haue been blynde, and haue not ſeene, and as dombe doges who haue not barked. The Lord appoynted us to be buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of his houſe, (the ground, corner, and headſtone whereof is <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi>)
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:6780:27"/>
but we haue been breakers downe of that, which our worthy prediceſſors, and we our ſelues haue builded up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and ſo <hi>haue made our ſelues tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Gal. 2.18</hi> The Lord appoynted us to be <hi>the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and dreſſers of his vineyard;</hi> but we, by our ſloath and ſilence, haue ſuffered the hedges therof to be broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe, and many wylde grapes to growe ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in. The Lord appoynted us to be <hi>the ſheephards of his flocke,</hi> to feed them, &amp; lead them out to the greene paſtures of his word and Sacraments: but we, in a great meaſure, haue been <hi>idle ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards, feading our ſelues, and forgetting the flocke, which Chriſt hath purchaſed with his pretious bloud.</hi> Here is the cauſe of our wounded &amp; hurt liberties. This we confeſſe in the ſight of God, and his Angels; for this we cry God mercy for Chriſts ſake. O that <hi>our heads were full of water, and our eyes a fountayne of teares, that we might weep day, and night,</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:6780:28"/>
&amp; bewayle this our miſery, never cea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſing &amp; keeping ſilence, <hi>till our God haue mercy upon us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet to ſearch out more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly the blame of our wounded liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Albeit we be all inwrapped in the guiltines thereof, yet ſome are deaper in the guiltines, then others. Who are theſe? Some of us not contented with our ſtanding in the Miniſtery, haue clombe up to higher places both in Church and Common wealth, then God hath called us unto; through co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſnes ſeeking the profitts of this preſent and periſhing life; through am<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bition affecting the preferments ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and imparity in power, and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity aboue their brethren; who, to winne to them preferment, haue trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled <hi>the peace of Ieruſalem,</hi> and hurt the liberties thereof.</p>
            <p>Yf any will ſay, it is parity (among Paſtors) in power and authority, that is the mother of confuſion, &amp; the brea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ker
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:6780:28"/>
of vnity; ſurely this is an unjuſt ſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of parity. For firſt it is the ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God, <hi>who is the author both of order, and peace.</hi> 1 Cor. 14.33. There was none of the Apoſtles in authority aboue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: none of the Evangeliſts in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aboue another: none of the Paſtors in authority aboue another; none of the Elders in authority aboue another. For they who keep one ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cke are in equall power. This practiſe hath the place of an ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Yea examine that place well, Math. 20.25.26.27. and out of <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſpeach to his Diſciples, upon the occaſion of the ſute of the ſonnes of <hi>Zebedeus,</hi> by conſequent ye ſhall draw out an ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Secondly, if any ſuch thing fall out where parity is, the fault is not to be layd upon the parity of power, but upon the impari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſpirits, which cannot ſatisfie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with the place, and power, that God hath give<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. Thirdly, all theſe imputations, may be layd juſtly upon
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:6780:29"/>
imparity, which is the mother of prid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that never can keep unity, and peace <hi>Only through pryde doth a man make con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tention,</hi> ſayth Salomon, Prov. 13.10.</p>
            <p>And if any will call to mynde the times paſſed, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ever there hath ben<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any trouble or ſtirre in our Church, they ſhall finde, that the authors, and inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of it were ever ſome, who, through covetouſnes &amp; ambition (the two banes of the church) haue ſought to themſelues, a preheminence among their brethren, whoſe deedes and <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphes</hi> may be a terror to thoſe, who tread in their footeſteppes. And to ſtrengthen the truth of this, we will borrow help from the Evangeliſt <hi>Iohn,</hi> 3. Ioh. 9.10. It appeares that there was a great ſtirre in that Church, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to he writeth; but who was the cauſer of it? One <hi>Diotrephes</hi> ſaith he. And what of him? <hi>He loved to haue the prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence among them.</hi> And what did he? <hi>He pratled among them with malitious
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:6780:29"/>
wordes.</hi> There is his ſlaunder. What more? <hi>He received not the brethren, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orbad them that would, and did thruſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut of the Church.</hi> There is his injury. And it may be alſo, he drew into the Church, againſt order, ſuch as might be proppes to his pryde. Then if this one <hi>Diotrephes</hi> had been removed out of that Church, all thinges had paſſed in peace, and quietnes therein.</p>
            <p>Now if we were charged upon life, and death, and in conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce before the Lord (according to the weakenes of our wit) to giue a rule for the peace &amp; quietnes of our Church; this it is: Ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther take away <hi>Demas</hi> and <hi>Diotrephes</hi> from office in the Church: or take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them their evill humors of covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and ambition: or take away their honors, the objects of great benefices, and Biſhopprickes: and then if any be found, who ſhall trouble their heads to hatch out an argument for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſe of ſo offenſiue a ſtate; and if then
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:6780:30"/>
               <hi>peace ſhall not be within the walles of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, and proſperity within the palaces thereof,</hi> we ſhall be content to beare the blame, and burden whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Agayne if any will ſay, that all this may be mended by this one meane; to make choyce of the moſt wiſe, graue, godly, and zealous of the Miniſtery, &amp; promote the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to thoſe places (which make greene, and unſetled witts quick<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly forget themſelues) and ſo all things ſhall go well, and be well governed: Surely, we will not be ſo uncharitable as to thinke, that ſuch men (albeit they were lying at their feete) would ſtoop downe to take them up, they being clogged with ſo many inconvenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces. Agayne, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith; <hi>Evill wordes cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt good manners;</hi> ſo we ſay, that evill courſes will corrupt good men. For, as long as a Miniſter keepeth himſelfe within the compaſſe of his calling, in humility and holines ſerving the Lord his God, he hath the gratious, &amp; fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:6780:30"/>
bleſſing of his God attending on him, and his labours. But, how ſoone ſoever he breakes the bounds thereof, ſeaking the world, and the profits, and preferments thereof, the fruitfull bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing departeth, and the fearefull curſe comes in the place thereof, to worke vpon him; and then we ſhall ſee, that, of all men of the earth, ſuch a Miniſter will become the moſt vayne, worldly, proud, and ambitious. And thus, of all this which hath been ſpoken, we ſee, that there is no preſervatiue for us, but <hi>to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d faſt in that liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made us free, that we be not entang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led agayne with the yoke of bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to conclude this exerciſe; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we are mett here to doe the worke of the Lord, let us firſt remember, and <hi>conſider from whence we are fallen,</hi> from what degree of loue, and liberty, that <hi>we may repent and doe the firſt workes, and amend,</hi> leaſt the Lord our God <hi>come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us ſhortly, and remoue our Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:6780:31"/>
out of his place.</hi> Agayne, <hi>If there be any conſolation in Chriſt, if any comforte of loue, if any fellowſhip of ſpirit, if any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion, and mercy, let us be like minded, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ſame loue, being of one accord, and of one iudgment, that nothing be done through contention or vayneglory, but in meeknes of minde, every one ſeeking not that which is his owne, but that which is Chriſts &amp;c.</hi> Thirdly, let our heartes and eyes be ſett <hi>upon the recompence of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, that incorruptible crowne of glorie, which the chiefe ſheapheard Ieſus ſhal bring with him in his hand, in his glorious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance</hi> to crowne them <hi>who ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere, and be found faithfull to the end;</hi> and not upon the reward, that is in the hand of man, which is in it ſelfe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, and oftimes corruptes the mindes of men, and drawes them out of the right way. Laſtly, let us ſo ſpeak here, and ſo doe here, and ſo behaue our ſelues here, as if we were upon our laſt bed, making our laſt will, ready to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:6780:31"/>
giue account, not to man only, but to the Lord our God himſelfe, both of the employment of our life, and the uſing and keeping of this liberty, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by our redeemer <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> hath made us free; To whom, with the Father, and ſpirit of grace, be honor, prayſe, and glory for ever, and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6780:32"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6780:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
